"Best Temperature, Timing, and Duration
for Cold Plunges for Athletic Performance Recovery"
In the last decade,
cold-water immersion
has emerged
as one of the most popular
post-exercise
recovery strategies
utilized among athletes
during training and competition.
This primarily stems
from the belief
that cold-water immersion
facilitates aspects
of recovery and regeneration,
thereby conferring
a potential training
and performance advantage.
But is it a friend, foe,
or just futile?
The cold truth...
is that local cryotherapy,
meaning like an ice pack,
does not appear
to diminish soreness
or accelerate
the recovery strength.
Local cryotherapy
does not seem to contribute
to the improvement
of delayed onset muscle soreness
or muscle weakness
associated with
exercise-induced muscle damage,
but what about cold plunges?
If you look at
the largest systematic review
and meta-analysis
of the effects of cold plunges
on the recovery
of physical performance,
compiling the results
of more than five dozen
randomized, controlled,
or crossover studies,
after cold-water immersion,
people felt less sore
after a workout,
at one hour later,
six hours later,
one day, two days,
and three days later,
but not after four days.
They also felt less fatigued,
particularly in the hour
or hours immediately afterwards.
And, after three days,
they reported feeling
more recovered
than those who hadn’t done
the cold plunges.
But were
they actually more recovered
using objective measures?
Endurance was significantly
improved an hour later,
but not after that.
Jump performance was impaired
six hours after the cold plunge
but was significantly improved
24 hours later.
Allow me a quick tangent
on heterogeneity.
See this i squared column?
This is something
I don’t talk about enough.
i squared is a number
between 0 and 100
and represents
the amount of variation
between studies that’s due
to true differences in effect
rather than just due to chance.
So, it’s a measure
of inconsistency.
The 0 percent here means that
there was perfect consistency;
so, any difference
in the results
was due just to random chance.
A low value like that
gives us more confidence
that we’re dealing
with a real effect.
But the 44 percent here
suggests more variability.
Check out
the individual studies.
Here are the results
of 29 studies
on the recovery
of muscular power performance
after high-intensity exercise.
If we put
all the studies together,
there may be a small benefit
favoring cold plunges,
but only about one in five
found statistically
significant benefit,
one found harm,
and the vast majority
found no significant effect.
Still, enough of the studies
leaned in the direction
of benefit to tip the scale.
In terms of sprint performance,
there was an initial
deterioration in performance,
but then none after that,
and a significant increase
in strength recovery
the next day.
This coincides with a lessening
of muscular damage indicators
the next day, lasting through
days two and three.
What are the best parameters
of cold plunges
in terms of timing,
temperature, and duration?
There really isn’t
a "gold standard,"
but the first systematic review
concluded that
cold-water immersion
at a temperature
between 11 and 15°C
for 11 15 minutes was best.
That’s like
in the 50s Fahrenheit.
However,
since that first review,
there’s been
a bunch more studies,
and the updated review
found that the water temperature
didn’t seem to matter,
whether severely cold at
5 to 9 degrees Celsius
(in the Fahrenheit 40s)
or that moderately cold
at 10 to 15°C,
but the immersion duration
did seem to matter.
Immersions lasting
less than ten minutes
presented better results
and plunging
for more than 16 minutes
didn’t seem to help at all.
And it’s better to immerse
immediately following exercise
rather than waiting.
Now, in most of these studies,
researchers used
passive recovery
in the control groups,
meaning people were randomized
to cold plunges
or to just, like, sit
in a chair for 20 minutes.
But who exercises intensely
and then just sits in a chair?
Many athletes use
active recovery
in the form
of a low-intensity "warm down"
to recover after exercise,
like walking around a bit
to keep the blood flowing,
getting rid of some
of that lactic acid buildup.
So, instead,
what about randomizing people
to cold-water immersion
versus normal active recovery?
That might be
a fairer comparison.
And in that case,
the cold plunge didn’t work.
It was no more effective
than active recovery.
Okay, but that’s just one study.
Let’s look at a meta-analysis
of all such studies
comparing the effects
of cold-water immersion
with other recovery modalities.
In terms of muscle soreness,
cold-water immersion
didn’t seem to work any better
than active recovery or any
of the other recovery methods,
including warm-water immersion.
Same for the recovery
of muscular power.
No significant difference
between cold plunging
and active recovery,
contrast water therapy,
which is like alternating
hot and cold,
warm-water immersion,
air cryotherapy,
like in a cryochamber,
massage,
or electrical stimulation.
If it’s all the same,
I think I might prefer
the massage to the plunge.
Same for the recovery of muscle
strength, no difference.
Immersing in cold water
did seem to beat out warm water
on perceived recovery, though,
but nothing else,
and it was the same with
flexibility, no difference,
and the same with measures
of muscle damage,
though electrifying your legs
did seem to work better
than the cold water.
The bottom line
is that all the recovery methods
seem to achieve about the same.
So, a cold plunge
may be better
than just sitting down
after intense exercise,
but there’s a wide range
of other practices
that appear to be
just as effective.
But any time doing something
beats out doing nothing,
you always have to ask if it
might just be a placebo effect.
You don’t know
if the perceived benefits
of cold plunges
are all in your head
until you put it to the test
with a placebo-controlled trial,
but how do you even do that?
We’ll find out, next.